A Guide to the John D. Wagg Papers, 1849-1894
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
John D. Wagg Papers, 1849-1894
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1992-048
0.4 Cubic Feet; 1 box
The John D. Wagg Papers, 1849-1894, documents the career and religious thoughts of Methodist preacher John D. Wagg and his fellow preachers, as well as the lives of his daughter Bettie Wagg, their family, and their friends. The collection contains correspondence, diaries and notebooks, sermons, church documents, and miscellaneous writings.
Wagg, John D., 1835-1866
Wagg, Bettie (Martha Elizabeth), 1863-1898
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
The John D. Wagg Papers were purchased by Special Collections and University Archives in November 1992 and August 2011.
Biographical Note
John D. Wagg, son of minister James Wagg, was born in Jefferson, North Carolina, on July 8, 1835. Although he initially studied medicine in 1854 at Jefferson Academy, Wagg eventually entered the ministry. On July 17, 1858, the Holston Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church South authorized and licensed him as a preacher. The Holston Conference, in the mid-nineteenth century, encompassed most of western North Carolina, eastern Tennessee, and southwestern Virginia.
Wagg's first appointments were in the Virginia counties of Giles, Russell, and Wise, where he labored as a circuit preacher. By 1859, however, he was reassigned to Hillsville, Virginia, where he married Lavinia "Vin" Anderson on May 13, 1862.
Wagg subsequently assumed ministerial duties in Asheville, North Carolina, in late 1862. His only child, Martha Elizabeth "Bettie" Wagg, was born there at the home of lawyer Joshua Roberts on March 6, 1863. On August 6, 1864, his wife Lavinia died.
In late 1864, John D. Wagg relocated to Bristol, Virginia, although he continued to deliver occasional sermons in Asheville. Wagg was superannuated by the Methodist Episcopal Church South in 1865 because of tuberculosis. He died in 1866.
Bettie Wagg attended Martha Washington College in Abingdon, Virginia, in the mid-1880s. She died on March 20, 1898, and is buried along with her father John D. Wagg in Hillsville, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The John D. Wagg Papers, 1849-1894, contain correspondence, diaries and notebooks, church documents, and miscellaneous poems and essays. Correspondence comprises letters to Wagg from ministers, family, and friends, 1858-1866, and letters between Bettie Wagg and her grandfather James Wagg and friends,1869-1894. Church documents include Wagg's credentials and a list of members and map of the Hillsville circuit. The diaries and notebooks include notes for and copies of sermons as well as information about church. There are also miscellanous poems and essays by Wagg and his wife Lavinia and daughter Bettie.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type.
Rights Statement for Archival Description
The guide to the John D. Wagg Papers by Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, is licensed under a CC0 (https://creativecommons.org/share-your- work/public-domain/cc0/).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Organizations:
Methodist Episcopal Church, South
People:
Wagg, Bettie (Martha Elizabeth), 1863-1898; Wagg, John D., 1835-1866
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1858-1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Josiah Torbett in Princeton, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, November 11, 1858
  - James K. Stringfield in Wytheville, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, December 14, 1858
  - [Unknown writer] in Stony Point, North Carolina, to Jno. [J. D. Wagg?], April 26, 1859
  - Josiah Torbett in Princeton, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, May 17, 1859
  - T. D. Summers in Boon's Creek, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, July 7, 1859
  - Josiah Torbett in Princeton, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, August 18, 1859
  - A. W. Wagg to "My Dear Brother" [J. D. Wagg?], October 22, 1859
  - A. W. Smith in Gladeville, Wise Courthouse, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, November 8, 1859
  - W. W. Neal in Athens, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, November 12, 1859
  - John. W. Mann in Hillsville, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, December 7, 1859
  - A. W. Smith in Wise Courthouse, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, December 23, 1859
- Correspondence, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - W. P. Quien in Wythe County, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, January 29, 1860
  - A. W. Smith in Wise County, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, February 13, 1860
  - John N. Jones in Taylorsville, North Carolina, to J. D. Wagg, February 28, 1860
  - John W. Mann in Hillsville, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, March 21, 1860
  - James Wagg in Jefferson, North Carolina, to J. D. Wagg, May 17, 1860
  - John W. Mann in Hillsville, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, June 21, 1860
  - J. W. M. [John W. Mann?] in Hillsville, Virginia, to Jonnie [J. D. Wagg?], July 25, 1860
  - James Wagg in Jefferson, North Carolina, to J. D. Wagg, August 1, 1860
- Correspondence, 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - J. D. Peters in Pearisburg, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, January 1, 1861
  - John D. Wagg in Hillsville, Virginia, to Samuel Wagg, February 18, 1861
  - A. J. Frazier in Rheatown, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, March 4, 1861
  - A. G. Pendleton in Fort Branch, [North Carolina?], to J. D. Wagg, March 5, 1861
  - A. J. Frazier in Rheatown, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, June 4, 1861
  - W. P. Quien in Grayson County, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, August 11, 1861
  - John [Wagg?], Jefferson, North Carolina, to Lavinia Anderson, December 14, 1861
    Scope and Content
    Includes two handwritten copies.
  - W. P. Quien in Ducktown, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, December 26, 1861
  - Gwen in Knoxville, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, February 11, 1862
  - J. M. McTeer in Speedwell, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, March 24, 1862
  - W. McDowell in Wytheville, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, April 11, 1862
  - Gwen in Knoxville, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, April 15, 1862
  - Gwen in Knoxville, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, May 25, 1862
  - John [Wagg] to Lavinia Anderson, [ca. May 1862]
  - James Wagg, Jefferson, North Carolina, to Lavinia Wagg, September 2, 1862
  - Benjamin W. S. Bishop in Jefferson, North Carolina, to J. D. Wagg, September 20, 1862
  - Lavinia Wagg, Asheville, North Carolina, to "Dear Sister", October 3, 1862
  - J. D. Wagg in Wytheville, Virginia, to "Vin" [Lavinia Wagg], October 11, 1862
    Includes typewritten transcription
  - Lavinia [Wagg], Hillsville, Virginia, to "Dear husband" [J. D. Wagg], October 14, 1862
  - F. L. Hale, Hillsville, Virginia, to J. D. and L. Wagg, November 19, 1862
  - Laura and John Wilkinson, Carroll County, Virginia, and [Hillsville?], Virginia, to "Vin" and "Dear Sister" [Lavinia Wagg], December 10, 1862
  - Lavinia and John Wagg, Asheville, North Carolina, to "Dear Sister", December 28, [1862]
  - M. Tatum to J. D. Wagg, with newspaper clipping, December 1862
- Correspondence, 1863-1866 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Samuel S. Grant in Hillsville, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, April 16, 1863
  - [Thena?], Hillsville, Virginia, to Lavinia and John Wagg, May 3, 1863
  - A. J. Frazier in Jacksboro, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, May 19, 1863
  - Samuel S. Grant in Hillsville, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, August 12, 1863
  - William H. Howell in Hendersonville, North Carolina, to J. D. Wagg, July 20, 1864
  - Invitation for the funeral of Lavinia Wagg, August 9, 1864
  - Joshua Roberts in Asheville, North Carolina, to J. D. Wagg, October 2, 1864
  - A. D. Stewart to J. D. Wagg, February 20, 1865
  - Joshua Roberts in Asheville, North Carolina, to J. D. Wagg, with newspaper clipping, February 24, 1865
  - J. D. Wagg, Bristol, Tennessee, to "Miss Laura", July 24, 1865
  - James R. Stringfield in Emory, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, September 21, 1865
  - A. D. Stewart in Chattanooga, Tennessee, to J. D. Wagg, December 28, 1865
  - J. B. Johnson in Lynchburg, Virginia, to J. D. Wagg, February 15, 1866
  - Josie in Rose Valley, [Pennsylvania?], to J. D. Wagg, May 1866
- Correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - M. Tatum to J. D. Wagg, 3 letters, n.d.
  - Anson W. Cummings at [Holston Conference] Female College, Asheville, North Carolina, to J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - J. D. Wagg to unknown person, n.d.
  - Elva in Hillsville, Virginia, to Lavinia Wilkerson, n.d.
  - Mollie to "My Dear Brother", n.d.
- Correspondence of Bettie Wagg, 1869, 1878-1879 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bettie Wagg, Etowah Seminary, to "My Darling Pet", August 21, 1869
  - James Wagg, Jefferson, North Carolina, to Bettie Wagg, March 11, 1878
  - James Wagg, Jefferson, North Carolina, to Bettie Wagg, December 2, 1878
  - Florence W., Marion Female College, Marion, Virginia, to "Ever Dear Cousin", [1878?]
  - James Wagg, Jefferson, North Carolina, to Bettie Wagg, February [4?], 1879
- Correspondence of Bettie Wagg, 1880-1894 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - James Wagg, Jefferson, North Carolina, to [Bettie Wagg], January 19, 1880
  - James Wagg, Jefferson, North Carolina, to [Bettie Wagg], July 22, 1880
  - Mattie, [Trinity?] Hall, to Bettie Wagg, January 9, 1880
  - Mattie, [Trinity?] Hall, to Bettie Wagg, June 2, 188[1?]
  - Annie Mustard, Wytheville, Virginia, to Bettie Wagg, November 27, 1884
  - Eva Fugate, Martha Washington College, to Bettie Wagg, January 28, 1885
    Includes short notes from "Mattie" and Lula [Umberger?].
  - L. R. [Inley?], Abingdon, Virginia, to Bettie Wagg, February 23, 1885
  - Eva [Fugate?], Martha Washington College, to Bettie Wagg, April 2[?], 1885
  - Eliza M., Martha Washington College, Virginia, to Bettie Wagg, April 12, 1885
  - Mary N. Wagg, Saltville, Virginia, to Bettie Wagg, June 28, 1886
  - Eliza F., Willow Spring, [North Carolina?], to Bettie Wagg, January 3, 1887
  - Mrs. R. R. Crow, District Secretary, per Mrs. M. J. W., Newbern, Virginia, to Bettie Wagg, March 7, 1889
  - Laura P. Wilkinson, Hillsville, Virginia, to Bettie Wagg, June 19, 1889
  - Bettie Wagg, Weaverville, North Carolina, to Laura, September 25, 1893
  - Mattie Maxon, Saint Louis, [Virginia?], to "Cousin Laura", January 25, 1894
- Diary of J D. Wagg, 1854-1858 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Pocket diary and almanac of J D. Wagg, 1865, 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes lock of hair and sheet with family data.
- Notebook of sermons by J. D. Wagg, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Sermons, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Trial of Faith" sermon by J. D. Wagg, preached on February 21, 1864, at Asheville, North Carolina, and on March 5, 1865, at Bristol, Virginia, February 21, 1864, March 5, 1865
  - "The Builders" sermon by J. D. Wagg, preached on February 19, 1865, at Bristol, Virginia, and on March 27, 1865, at Asheville, North Carolina, February 19, 1865, March 27, 1865
  - "Angels" sermon by J. D. Wagg, preached on March 15, 1865, at Asheville, North Carolina, March 15, 1865
  - "Faith" sermon by J. D. Wagg, preached on June 15, 1865, at Asheville, North Carolina, and on June 18, 1865, at Bristol, Virginia, June 15, 1865, June 18, 1865
- Sermons, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "A New Creature" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "Aspiration of the Scriptures--External Evidence" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "God Seen in Nature" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "Praise" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "The Divinity of Christ" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "The Fall of Man" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "The Lord God and Death" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "The Water of Life" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "Valedictory" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "What of the Night?" sermon by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
- Notes for sermons, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous church documents and writings, 1849, 1858, 1884, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Class book for Hillsville, Virginia, congregation of the Holston Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church South, n.d.
    Compiled by J. M. McTeer and J. D. Wagg, this book includes names of church members.
  - Map of Hillsville, Virginia, circuit of the Holston Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church South, n.d.
  - Church credentials of J. D. Wagg, January 1, 1858
  - Church credentials of J. D. Wagg, July 17, 1858
  - Poem signed by Lavinia Anderson, March 15, 1849
  - "To Miss _____" poem by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - "Mocking Bird" poem by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - Poem by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - Two essays by J. D. Wagg, n.d.
  - History Examination, Bettie Wagg, Martha Washington College, November 15, 1884